<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5245 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5389 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5389.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4594 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4594.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<?rfc tocindent='yes' ?>
<?rfc comments='yes' ?>
<?rfc inline='yes' ?>

<?rfc needLines="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-martinsen-tram-discuss-latest" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DISCUSS">Differentiated prIorities and Status
      Code-points Using Stun Signalling (DISCUSS)</title>

    
    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 20</street>
          <city>Lysaker</city>
          <region>Akershus</region>
          <code>1366</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Herb Wildfeuer" initials="H" surname="Wildfeuer">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>821 Alder Drive</street>
          <city>Milpitas</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code>95035</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>hwildfeu@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <workgroup>TRAM</workgroup>
    
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This draft describes a mechanism for information exchange
        between an application and the network.  The information
        provided from the application to the network MAY be used by a
        network element in the path to modify its behavior to improve
        application quality of experience (QoE).  Likewise, the
        information provided by the network to the application MAY be
        used by the application to modify its behavior to optimize for
        QoE.
      </t>
      <t>
          The information provided from the application to the network can also 
          be useful for middleboxes that are responsible for security at edges
          of network (e.g. firewalls) or other middleboxes in determining
          how to treat the packets delivered from this application. 
      </t>
    </abstract>
    
    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        In the context of Content, Mobile, Fixed Service, Service
        Providers, Enterprise and Private networks have a need to
        prioritize packet flows end-to-end. These flows are often
        dynamic, time-bound, encrypted, peer-to-peer, possibly
        asymmetric, and might have different priorities depending on
        network conditions, direction, time of the day, dynamic user
        preferences and other factors. These factors may be time
        variant, and thus need to be signalled. Moreover, in many
        cases of peer-to-peer communication, flow information is known
        only to the endpoint. These considerations, coupled with the
        trend to use encryption for browser-to-browser communication
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch"/>, imply that
        access lists, deep packet inspection and other static
        prioritization methods cannot be employed successfully to
        prioritize packet flows. 
      </t>
      <t>
        The lack of congestion control in UDP may lead to problems as
        described in <xref target="I-D.eggert-tsvwg-rfc5405bis"/>. The
        mechanism described in this document can be used to introduce
        fairness and congestion control for UDP streams.
      </t>
      <t>
        There is a need for a solution that is easy for the
        application developer to use. That means consistent behavior
        on all supported platforms and preferably without need of
        administrative privileges to set and read values. The solution
        also needs to be able to cross administrative domains without
        the risk of being rewritten. 
        <cref anchor="Q1" source="palmarti">
          This draft will only offer
          tamper detection of some of the values. Further discussion
          regarding the incentive to lie is needed.   
        </cref>
      </t>
      <!--
      <t>
        Todo: Say why we want to have a simpler solution than <xref
        target="RFC6679"/>.
      </t>
      -->
      <t>
        This draft describes how these problems can be solved by
        defining a few strictly defined STUN <xref target="RFC5389"/>
        attributes which can be added to any STUN message the client
        wants to send. STUN messages are typically sent during the ICE
        <xref target="RFC5245"/> connectivity check phase when the
        media session is established, or when keep-alive STUN messages
        are sent after the session is established. The application is
        not limited to those two scenarios, if some communication
        between application and network is needed it can choose to do
        so at any time.
      </t>
      <t>
        Devices on the media path can use the information in the STUN
        attributes to prioritize the flow, perform traffic
        engineering, provide network analytics or as a gateway to
        existing methods for prioritizing flows (DSCP
        <xref target="RFC2474"/>). Applications can use information in
        network status attribute to influence rate stating points or
        rate adaption mechanisms.
      </t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="General Usage">
      <t>
        This draft defines several attributes that can be added to a
        STUN message; STREAM-TYPE, BANDWIDTH-USAGE, STREAM-PRIORITY
        and NETWORK-STATUS. See <xref target="new_attributes" /> for
        the formal description. It is RECOMMENDED to add them to a
        STUN request response pair, especially if the NETWORK-STATUS
        attribute is in use. This allows the information gathered to
        be sent back to the requesting agent in the the STUN response.
      </t>
      <t>
        The STREAM-TYPE, BANDWIDTH-USAGE, STREAM-PRIORITY attributes
        MUST be added before any INTEGRITY attribute. It is
        RECOMMENDED to only add these attributes to STUN messages
        containing a INTEGRITY attribute as this prevents tampering
        with the content of the attribute.
      </t>
      <t>
        If the client wants to receive feedback from the network it
        must add a null NETWORK-STATUS attribute. A null
        NETWORK_STATUS attribute is created by filling in the all the
        fields in the attribute with 0x0 values. This attribute MUST
        be added after the INTEGRITY attribute, as on-path devices may
        write information into this attribute. Having a readily
        available attribute to write into will save the the on-path
        device from growing buffers to add their own attribute. On
        path devices SHOULD not add their own NETWORK-STATUS attribute
        (or any other STUN attribute).
      </t>
      <t>
        If an agent receives a STUN request with a NETWORK-STATUS
        attribute after the INTEGRITY attribute, it should copy the
        content into a new NETWORK-STATUS attribute and add it before
        the INTEGRITY attribute when sending the STUN response. A new
        null NETWORK-STATUS attribute can be added after the INTEGRITY
        attribute. New STUN attributes described in this draft can
        also be added describing the stream in this direction.
      </t>
      <t>
        If an agent receives a STUN response with a NETWORK-STATUS
        attribute before the INTEGRITY attribute, this describes the
        stream in the upstream direction. A NETWORK-STATUS attribute
        after the INTEGRITY attribute describes the stream in the
        downstream direction.
      </t>
      <t>
        It might make sense to distinguish DISCUSS packets from normal STUN
        packets. This would prevent unnecessary processing of normal
        STUN packets on the network nodes.
      </t>
      <t><cref anchor="Q2" source="palmarti">
        A few alternatives (Needs discussion):
        ---1: 
            Alter the STUN magic cookie. (But than i would not be a
            STUN packet anymore, and that raises a new set of
            problems)
        ---2:
            Add a special this is DISCUSS attribute. This must be the
            first attribute in the message. This allows for network
            node to look for DISCUSS packets at a fixed offset without
            needing to parse the entire packet.
        ---3:
            Alter the transaction id. This might be problematic if
            using it in conjunction with ICE connectivity checks. But
            probably fine in other scenarios.
        ---4:  
            Define a new STUN Method. Also brakes ICE, makes it
            harder to tag onto attributes to already in use messages.
        </cref>
      </t>
      <t>
        <cref anchor="Q3" source="palmarti">Do we want to restrict
          this to req/resp or do we want to allow for the attributes
          to be added in this fashion for indications as well?</cref>
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure title="DISCUSS example flow">
        <artwork><![CDATA[  
  Alice                router1            router2              Bob
   |                      |                   |                  |
   |Binding_Request       |                   |                  |
(1)|--------------------->|(2)                |                  |
   |                      |                   |                  |
   |                      |Binding_Request    |                  |
   |                      |------------------------------------->|
   |                      |                   |                  |
   |                      |                   | Binding_Response |
   |                      |                   |<-----------------|(3)
   |                      |  Binding_Response |                  |
   |<-----------------------------------------|(4)               |
   |(5)                   |                   |                  |

]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Alice creates a Binding Request, adds STREAM-TYPE,
            BANDWIDTH-USAGE, STREAM-PRIORITY attributes before the
            INTEGRITY attribute and a single null NETWORK-STATUS
            attribute after the INTEGRITY attribute.
          </t>              
          <t>
            Router1 inspects the STUN Request message and reads any
            STREAM-TYPE, BANDWIDTH-USAGE, or STREAM-PRIORITY
            attributes and the information they contain. It then
            updates the NETWORK-STATUS attribute with any information
            the router have. It then forwards the request.
          </t>
          <t>
            Bob processes the STUN Request. When Bob builds the
            response, it copies the NETWORK-STATUS attribute into the
            STUN Response before the INTEGRITY check and adds new null
            NETWORK-STATUS attribute after the INTEGRITY
            attribute. Bob then transmits the message.
          </t>
          <t>
            Router2 (first DISCUSS network element for the downstream
            direction) inspects the Response message, reads the
            STREAM-TYPE, BANDWIDTH-USAGE, or STREAM-PRIORITY
            attributes and MAY alter the NETWORK-STATUS attribute
            located after the INTEGRITY attribute. It then transmits
            the message.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Alice receives the STUN Response, she can extract the
            STREAM-TYPE, BANDWIDTH-USAGE, or STREAM-PRIORITY
            attributes and the two NETWORK-STATUS attributes to get a
            complete picture of what the remote agent is sending and
            how the status of both the upstream and downstream path.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Network Processing">
      <t> 
        This section describes the processing of DISCUSS packets by
        network devices.
      </t>
      <section title="Packet Processing by Network Device">
        <t>
          Network devices are said to support DISCUSS if they perform
          inspection of packets being forward or switched in order to
          identify an DISCUSS STUN packet.  These devices will also be
          able to read/write STUN attributes to/from this packet.  It
          is not required that every network device in the path
          support DISCUSS.  It is expected that DISCUSS will have the
          most value being implemented at certain points in the
          network (PIN's) such as WAN edge devices, wireless access
          devices, and Internet gateways.
        </t>
        <t>
          Network devices that support DISCUSS MAY utilize the
          information provided by the application in the STUN
          attributes to modify their behavior.  These include the
          attributes defined in this document with the exception of
          the NETWORK-STATUS attribute.  The NETWORK-STATUS attribute
          SHOULD NOT be used by the DISCUSS capable network device to
          modify its behavior.  The intent of the NETWORK-STATUS
          attribute is for the application to modify its behavior.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the NETWORK-STATUS attributes exists in a DISCUSS packet
          after an INTEGRITY attribute, the DISCUSS capable network
          device MUST process it as described in this section.
          NETWORK-STATUS attributes that exist before the INTEGRITY
          attribute MUST NOT be modified by the network device.  The
          modifications to the NETWORK-STATUS attribute are:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t> Update the Node Cnt field in the attribute.  The
              device SHALL increment this field by one unless it is at
              its maximum (saturated) value.  If the field is at its
              maximum value, the device SHALL NOT modify this field.
            </t>
            <t>
              Overwrite the attribute CS bit if the value at this
              device is "worst" than the current value.  In other
              words, only write to this bit if the device is
              experiencing congestion on relevant queues/interfaces
              for this flow AND the current value of this field is 0
              (Off).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The determination of congestion at a device is out of the
          scope of this document.  Setting of CS bit to On by the
          device is meant to provide direct feedback to the
          application of potential or current loss of packets in its
          flow (s).  The application can then react to this indication
          by altering its encoding of information in the packet to
          deal with congestion/packet loss, e.g. reduce its encoding
          rate or switch to embedded encoding.  Devices SHOULD ensure
          that the DISCUSS capable applications that do react to
          congestion notification by reducing their transmission rate
          be treated properly to ensure fairness with non reacting
          applications (i.e. ensure fairness for well behaving
          applications).
        </t>
        <t>
          The DISCUSS STUN packet SHOULD experience minimal extra
          processing delay through the DISCUSS capable network device
          relative to non-DISCUSS packets in the flow.  The DISCUSS
          STUN packet MAY be placed out of order in the packet flow,
          but SHOULD NOT be delayed more than a few packet interval
          times.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Interaction with DSCP">
        <t>
          One of the attributes that may be added to the STUN packet
          by the application is the STREAM-PRIORITY attribute.  This
          attribute indicates the relative priority of streams inside
          of an application session.  This attribute is compatible
          with the use of DSCP (or other priority markings) at the
          networking layer as described in this section.
        </t>
        <t>
          Since transport layer markings may be modified by middle
          boxes or devices in the path or at the interface of the
          application itself due to the lack of support in the OS
          network stack, the STREAM-PRIORITY attribute can be used as
          a mechanism for ensuring proper QoS treatment through
          multiple domains.  DISCUSS capable device may use the
          STREAM-PRIORITY attribute to remark the DSCP value to the
          appropriate value.  DSCP re-marking based on STREAM-PRIORITY
          attribute may make sense at certain PIN's, e.g. gateway
          between network domains (e.g. managed network to/from
          Internet), access switches in managed network, etc.  The
          translation from the Priority number in the STREAM-PRIORITY
          attribute to the correct transport layer marking (e.g. DSCP)
          is implementation specific and out of the scope of this
          document.
        </t>
        <t>
          <xref target="I-D.dhesikan-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos"/> provides the
          recommended DSCP values for webrtc enabled browsers to use
          for various classes of traffic.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
<section title="Interaction with ICE">
      <t>
        An ICE connectivity check is performed by sending a STUN
        Binding indication. Prior to sending the agent can add one
        STREAM-TYPE attribute. If added, only one MUST be added. This
        is to avoid unnecessary large STUN packets during the
        connectivity checks. If the connectivity check is sent on a
        5-tuple that multiplexes different types of media and more
        detailed information wants to be signalled it should be done
        after the connectivity check phase is finished.
      </t>
      <t>
        This limits the information the STUN messages are able to
        convey during the connectivity checks, but also avoids adding
        network confusion with BANDWIDTH-USAGE attributes describing
        different paths that never going to be utilized.
      </t>
      <t>
        <cref anchor="Q4" source="palmarti">
          Problem with consent freshness if not based on STUN.
        </cref>
      </t>  
      
    </section>
    <section title="Multiplexed Streams">
      <t>
        In some scenarios a 5-tuple can be used to transport several
        media streams. BUNDLE
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-sdp-bundle-negotiation" />
        describes such a mechanism.
      </t>
      <t>
          At times, the different "streams" carried in this bundle require very
          different treatment from the network, including the ability to 
          prioritize some of these "streams" over others.  For example, the 
          application my bundle video and audio in the same 5-tuple flow,
          but would like the network to prioritize the delivery of audio
          over that of video in the case of congestion.  Another example is
          the use of embedded (or scalable) coding for video.  
          Per <xref target="RFC6190">RFC 6190</xref>,
          using Multi-session Transmission (MST)
          the
          layers are transported in seperate sub-flows (RTP sessions) within the 
          bundled flow.
          Using the STREAM-TYPE
          attribute with the extension to identify the sub-flow and its 
          priority would allow
          network elements, if capable, to provide differentiated services
          even in the case of bundling.
      </t>
      <t>
          For RTP/SRTP based flows,
          the existence and attributes for sub-flows in the flow MAY be indicated by the 
          application
          via the SUB-STREAM-xxx attributes.  These
          attributes MUST only be included if the equivalent STREAM-xxxx 
          attributes are included.  It is expected that only
          a sub-set of network elements representing bottleneck Points in 
          Network (PIN) will be able to inspect the higher
          layer protocols to differentiate sub-flows, so it is important
          to describe the agregate flow, and then the sub-flows.
          The SUB-STREAM-xxxx attributes are similar
          to the corresponding STREAM-xxxx attributes with the addition of
          the application layer identifier field.  For the case of RTP/SRTP,
          this field is the SSRC assigned to the flow.  Note that this will
          only work for non-header encrypted SRTP.
      </t>
      <t>
        When describing the aggregate stream with a STREAM-TYPE attribute there
        are two possibilities to describe the streams that are
        multiplexed. Adding one attribute for each type (Audio,
        Video,++), or to save a few bits on the wire it is also
        possible to construct the STREAM-TYPE so a one type value
        describes several types. For example audio have the value of 1
        and application data have the value of 4. If the STREAM_TYPE
        value is set to 5 the only combination that gives that is
        audio and application data.  As previously discussed, in the case of 
          bundling, the agregate stream attribute MUST be included before the 
          optional sub-stream attributes
      </t>
      <t>
        The other attributes BANDWIDTH-USAGE, STREAM-PRIORITY and
        NETWORK-STATUS SHOULD only be added once as they describe the
        behavior of the 5-tuple and not individual streams.
      </t>
    </section>
        
    <section title="New STUN attributes" anchor="new_attributes" >
      <t>
        This STUN extension defines the following new attributes:
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
      0xXXX0: STREAM-TYPE
      0xXXX1: BANDWIDTH-USAGE
      0xXXX2: STREAM-PRIORITY
      0xXXX8: SUB-STREAM-TYPE
      0xXXX9: SUB-BANDWIDTH-USAGE
      0xXXXA: SUB-STREAM-PRIORITY
      0xYYYY: NETWORK-STATUS
           ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <section title="STREAM-TYPE">
        <t>
          This attribute have a length that are multiples of 4 (32) so
          no padding is necessary.
        </t>
        
        <figure anchor="stream_type_attr" title="STREAM TYPE Attribute">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|              TYPE             | Interactivity |               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="TYPE:"> STREAM TYPE is a 16 bit value
              defined in <xref target="stream_types"></xref> below describing the flow.
              <figure anchor="stream_types" title="STREAM Types">
                <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     0x0001 Audio
     0x0002 Video
     0x0004 Application Data
     0x0008 Other
                 ]]></artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
            <t hangText="Interactivity:"> Is a 8 bit value
              defined in <xref target="interactivity_types" /> below describing the flow.
              <figure anchor="interactivity_types" title="Interactivity Types">
                <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     0x00 Undef
     0x01 Stream (Broadcast? Oneway?)
     0x02 Interactive
                     ]]></artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
        <t>
          It is possible to combine the stream types if a stream
          contains more than one type. 
        </t>
        <t>
          If a 5-tuple is used to send both a audio and video stream,
          the stream type can be set to 0x0006. This can be useful if
          the application wants to hint that the 5-tuple contains
          several streams, This is useful if the attribute is added to
          STUN binding requests during ICE connectivity checks. If
          more information regarding multiplexed streams is needed it
          is possible to add more than one attribute to a STUN message
          (See section ??). This can be done to STUN messages that are
          being sent after the connectivity check phase is finished
          (Keep-alive, consent freshness). During this phase the added
          size of the STUN messages pose no security threat.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="BANDWIDTH-USAGE">
        <t>
          This attribute have a length that are multiples of 4 (32) so
          no padding is necessary.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="bandwidth_usage_attr" title="BANDWIDTH USAGE Attribute">
          <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|             AVERAGE (kbps)    |           MAX (kbps)          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="AVERAGE:"> Expected sustained bandwidth usage
              for this stream. Note that for elastic types of streams
              like video, sudden large movements in the picture my
              lead to this value being inaccurate.
            </t>
            <t hangText="MAX:"> The maximum bandwidth usage for this
              stream. If the sustained and max value differ greatly it
              might be safe to assume that an elastic encoder is in
              use. (Would it be useful to say something about expected
              BURST lengths?)
            </t>
            
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="STREAM-PRIORITY">
        <t>
          This attribute have a length that are multiples of 4 (32) so
          no padding is necessary.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="stream_priority_attr" title="STREAM PRIORITY Attribute">
          <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Priority      |D|    TBD      |           Stream IDX          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           Session ID                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            
            <t hangText="Priority:"> Describes this streams priority
              among other streams coming from this
              endpoint/application (With same session ID). Values
              range from 255 (0xFF) to 0.
            </t>
            <t hangText="D:"> Delay sensitive. The application can set
              this bit as a hint to the network element that the
              stream is delay sensitive. (Unsure if this is useful)
            </t>
            <t hangText="Stream IDX:"> Application can choose set this
              to ease debugging in the network. A reasonable value can
              foe example be the index have in the SDP.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Session ID:"> Identification to distinguish
              what session this stream is part of. This MUST have the
              same value for all the media streams the application
              wants to give differentiated services. (Note that this
              ID may overlap with other streams that originates from a
              different IP address. The network element MUST only
              prioritize among streams with the same Session Id
              originating from the same IP)
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
           
      <section title="NETWORK-STATUS">
        <t>
          This attribute have a length that are multiples of 4 (32) so
          no padding is necessary. The values are kept in the same
          attribute to make it easier for the network element to
          process it. Only one attribute, with static placement of the
          fields.
          <cref anchor="Q5" source="palmarti">
            Does this matter? Could we have several attributes with
            possible different ordering without any problem for the
            network element?
          </cref>
        </t>
        <t>
          This attribute MUST be added after any INTEGRITY attribute
          in the STUN message. Values in this attribute can be updated
          along the network path by nodes that are not able to
          regenerate a correct INTEGRITY attribute.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="network_status_attr" title="NETWORK-STATUS Attribute">
          <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|C|    Flags    | Node Cnt      |             TBD               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Up MAX Bitrate  (kbps)      | Down MAX Bitrate  (kbps)      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

 
      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="C:"> Congestion Status.  This bit is set to
            indicate that there is congestion at the network device's
            relevant queues/interfaces for this flow.  The network
            element should set this bit to 1 (On) if it is
            experiencing congestion.  This bit is set to 0 (off) when
            the attribute is created by the application.  The
            application that sees this bit set might act on it by
            doing some rate adaption or similar action.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Flags:"> 7 more bits available for flags.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Node Cnt:"> Numbers of nodes that supports
            DISCUSS in the network path. Any router on the path that
            understands DISCUSS should increase this number.  This
            field is set to 0 when the attribute is created by the
            application.
            </t>
            <t hangText="TBD:"> 16 more bits available for useful info.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Up MAX Bitrate:"> Available MAX bit-rate the
            router is able to handle for the 5-tuple in the UP
            direction. (Same direction as the packet is moving)
            </t>
            <t hangText="Down MAX Bitrate:"> Available MAX bit-rate the
            router is able to handle for the 5-tuple in the DOWN
            direction. (Opposite direction as the packet is moving)
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="SUB-STREAM-TYPE, SUB-STREAM-PRIORITY">
          <t>
          These attributes are identical format to their aggregate stream version
          (STREAM-TYPE, STREAM-PRIORITY) 
          with the addition of a transport layer identifier.  The transport
          layer identifier is a 64 bit field which contains the unique identifier
          of the sub-stream for which the attribute applies.
          </t>
          <t>
          Currently, only RTP transport is supported with the identifier being
          the SSRC currently used by the sub-stream.
          </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        IANA is requested to add the following attributes to the <xref
        target="iana-stun">STUN attribute registry</xref>, 
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            0xXXX0: STREAM-TYPE      (0xXXX0, in the comprehension-optional range)
          </t>
          <t>
            0xXXX1: BANDWIDTH-USAGE  (0xXXX1, in the comprehension-optional range)
          </t>
          <t>
            0xXXX2: STREAM-PRIORITY  (0xXXX2, in the comprehension-optional range)
          </t>
          <t>
            0xYYYY: NETWORK-STATUS   (0xYYYY, in the comprehension-optional range)
          </t>
        </list> 
      </t>
    </section>

    
    <section title="Implementation Status">
      <t>
        [Note to RFC Editor: Please remove this section and reference to
        <xref target="RFC6982"></xref> prior to publication.]
      </t>

      <t>
        This section records the status of known implementations of the
        protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
        Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref
        target="RFC6982"></xref>. The description of implementations in this
        section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in
        progressing drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any
        individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
        Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information
        presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not
        intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available
        implementations or their features. Readers are advised to note that
        other implementations may exist.
      </t>

      <t>
        According to <xref target="RFC6982"></xref>, "this will allow
        reviewers and working groups to assign due consideration to documents
        that have the benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of
        valuable experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented
        protocols more mature. It is up to the individual working groups to use
        this information as they see fit".
      </t>
      
      <section title="NATtools">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Organization: ">Cisco 
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Description: "> 
              Open-Source ICE, TURN and STUN implementation. 
            </t> 
            
            <t hangText="Implementation: ">
              https://github.com/cisco/NATTools
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Level of maturity: ">
              Code is stable. Tests
              being run to learn more on how to leverage the information
              shared between client and network.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Coverage: ">
              Implements the DISCUSS attributes
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Licensing: ">
              BSD
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Implementation experience: ">
              Draft was implemented with internal video test
              clients. Wireless access point implemented STUN
              detection in the media path and acted on the information
              in the DISCUSS attributes. After running tests in
              different congestion scenarios it is clear that sharing
              information between endpoint and network can help with
              congestion and end-user experience. This approach
              required little effort to implement on the client side.
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Contact: ">
              Paal-Erik Martinsen
              &lt;palmarti@cisco.com&gt;.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        Due to the security implications described in <xref
        target="I-D.thomson-mmusic-ice-webrtc"></xref> where large
        STUN packet are used to amplify an attack, keeping the added
        STUN attributes small is a important design consideration.
      </t>
      <t>
        To avoid unwanted information leakage the new defined STUN
        attributes defined in this draft are strictly defined. No more
        information should be leaked that an on-path device could
        learn by observing the stream over time or do some deep packet
        analysis. This draft would benefit from more discussions on
        this topic.
      </t>
      <t>
        It is also worth noticing that the STUN attributes defined
        should be treated as hints, and more work is needed regarding
        how to deal with misbehaving clients or network devices.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        Authors would like to thank Dan Wing, Anca Zamfir and Cullen
        Jennings for their comments and review.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119; 
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2474"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6190"?>
      <!--<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6679"?>-->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6982"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informational References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.thomson-mmusic-ice-webrtc' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.dhesikan-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-sdp-bundle-negotiation' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.eggert-tsvwg-rfc5405bis' ?>
       
      <reference anchor="iana-stun"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/stun-parameters/stun-pa rameters.xml">
        <front>
          <title>IANA: STUN Attributes</title>
          <author fullname="IANA" surname="IANA">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <!--<?rfc include='reference.I-D.muthu-behave-consent-freshness' ?>-->
    </references>
    <!--
      -->
  </back>
</rfc>

